<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present duty and endeavour of the saints. Opened in a sermon at Pauls upon the Lords day December, 14th. 1645. / By Joseph Caryl, minister of the Gospell at Magnus neere London-Bridge.</title>
            <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E323_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200589</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861301</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861301</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113433</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E323[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present duty and endeavour of the saints. Opened in a sermon at Pauls upon the Lords day December, 14th. 1645. / By Joseph Caryl, minister of the Gospell at Magnus neere London-Bridge.</title>
                  <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Forcet for George Hurlock, and are to be sold at his shop at Magnus-corner.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Ephesians V, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113433:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113433:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRESENT Duty and Endeavour OF THE SAINTS.</p>
            <p>Opened in a Sermon at <hi>Pauls</hi> upon the Lords day <hi>December,</hi> 14.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1645.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOSEPH CARYL, Miniſter of the Goſpell at <hi>Magnus</hi> neere <hi>London</hi>-Bridge.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by T. FORCET for GEORGE HURLOCK, and are to be ſold at his Shop at <hi>Magnus</hi>-corner. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113433:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113433:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable, THOMAS ADAMS Lord MAIOR of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">J</seg> Have (though ſomewhat late) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed your deſires for the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of this Sermon. The Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance it found with <hi>your Selfe</hi> gives me a ground of hope, that it was not unacceptable to others; The judgement of thoſe who are (as your Selfe is) in place of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent dignity and Authority, is (uſually) the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of inferiour judgements. And while our <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates</hi> give Teſtimony of their reliſhing ſuch a Doctrine as this, I am much perſwaded, that God is bringing it to the reliſh of all his people. <hi>When the Kingdomes</hi> (that is the people) <hi>of this world, ſhall become the kingdomes of the Lord and
<pb facs="tcp:113433:3"/> of his CHRIST,</hi> Then (doubtleſſe) <hi>Kings and Magiſtrates</hi> in all the World ſhall become the <hi>Lords and his Chriſts.</hi> All their <hi>Policies</hi> ſhall be turned into Piety, and their Conſultations into a zealous <hi>Proving what is Acceptable to the Lord.</hi> That <hi>your Lordſhip</hi> with thoſe <hi>venerable Colleagues</hi> the <hi>Magiſtrates of this City</hi> may doe ſo, and that All the people of this City eying as chiefly the warrant of the Word, ſo likewiſe your worke, as a ſhining Preſident, may doe ſo, is the prayer (as much as that in ſo doing your <hi>Hon: <hi rend="sup">ble</hi> Selfe,</hi> and this renowned City un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your government ſhall be happie, is the aſsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SIR, Your humble Servant in this worke of the Lord, JOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Januar. 22. d, 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113433:3"/>
            <head>THE PRESENT DUTY AND ENDEAVOUR OF THE SAINTS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EPHES. 5. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Proving what is acceptable to the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Aturals in <hi>working,</hi> are ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their <hi>being;</hi> Grapes grow not on thornes, nor Figgs upon thiſtles. While our Natures continue darke we cannot but do the works of darkneſſe. They who are Spirituall ſhould act ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually: And when they are in the light, it is their duty to be alwaies doing works of light: Thus the Apoſtle argues at the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe of this Chap. <hi>Ye were ſometimes darkneſſe, but now are yee light in the Lord: walke as children of the light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leſt any ſhould <hi>be in the darke</hi> about this duty, what it is to <hi>walke as children of the light,</hi> the Apoſtle
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113433:4"/> ſteps aſide into a Patentheſis, at the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe to explain it, <hi>The fruit of the Spirit</hi> (who or which is light) <hi>is in all goodneſse and righteouſneſſe and truth.</hi> To walke in goodneſſe and righteouſneſſe and truth, is, <hi>to walke as children of the light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe light is a helpe to diſcovery (light makes manifeſt) therefore the children of Light are not only called to doe their duty, but are warned to ſee, that it is a duty which they doe, <hi>Proving what is acceptable to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That's the buſineſſe of the text, upon which I ſhall inſiſt, when I have briefly opened; Firſt, what it is <hi>to prove;</hi> Secondly, what is meant by a thing <hi>Acceptable to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Greeke word, tranſlated <hi>Proving,</hi> ſignifies alſo <hi>Approving,</hi> and includes <hi>Practiſing.</hi> In the firſt ſence it is taken two wayes; Firſt, for proving by way of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or Experiment; Secondly, by way of Reaſon or Argument.</p>
            <p>The former way, he that had bought <hi>five yoke of Oxen, went to prove them, Luk.</hi> 14. 19. The Apoſtle ſpeakes of the proofe or <hi>tryall of Faith, which is much more precious then of Gold that periſheth (1 Pet.</hi> 1. 7.) The word bearing a native Alluſion to the tryall of mettals, eſpecially of Gold by the Teſt, or by the Touch-ſtone. Thus his Canon tels us, that <hi>Deacons</hi> muſt be proved: <hi>then let them uſe the office of a Deacon, being found</hi> (upon proofe) <hi>blameleſſe, 1 Tim.</hi> 3. 10. And thus all who profeſſe CHRIST, are exhorted to <hi>Prove themſelves, whether they be in the Faith, 2 Cor.</hi> 13. 5.</p>
            <p>Beſides this experimentall proofe of things and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113433:4"/> there is a logicall or a rationall proofe of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, of which we muſt underſtand that rule given the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> (1 Epiſt. 5. 21) <hi>Prove all things, hold fast that which is good.</hi> To this kind of proofe the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Text is chiefly to be referred.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Proving,</hi> the word caries us to <hi>Approving;</hi> the former convinces the judgement, this latter touch-es the will and affections. We have this tranſlation, <hi>Rom. 14. 22. Bleſſed is he that condemneth not himſelfe, in that thing which he alloweth, or approveth.</hi> And in the Paſſive moode (1 <hi>Cor. 11. 19.) There muſt be alſo Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies among you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt among you.</hi> Approved ones are <hi>currant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,</hi> in the ſence, wee call that <hi>Currant money,</hi> which is allowed in all payments.</p>
            <p>To both theſe acts of Probation and approbation, we may adde a third upon the uſage of this word; namely Practiſe, <hi>Rom. 12. 2. Be not conformed to this World, but be yee transformed by the renewing of your minds, that yee may prove what is that good, and that acceptable and perfect will of God.</hi> When the higher and nobler faculties of the Soule are renewed the whole man is transformed. New apprehenſions of things by the mind caſt a man into a new mould, and then as <hi>his Reaſon proves</hi> by diſcerning, and his <hi>Will by approving;</hi> ſo his <hi>actions prove</hi> by <hi>Practiſing</hi> what the acceptable will of God is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To be Acceptable,</hi> imports more then to <hi>be Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> The compoſition of the word increaſes the ſence<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non ſimplicite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſed</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne placitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et per gratum.</hi> Zanch.</note> of it, into <hi>Well-pleaſing</hi> or <hi>very well-pleaſing,</hi> yea <hi>Beſt-pleaſing;</hi> In this language the Apoſtle exhorts Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to be <hi>obedient to their owne Maſters, and to pleaſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113433:5"/> them well, (Tit.</hi> 2. 9) or to give them all content. The duty of a Servant is not reached in doing only ſo much as may ſerve his turne, to keepe his Maſter from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angry with him, but he ſhould labour to winne his Love, and to the utmoſt gaine his favour. The word is tranſlated <hi>Well-pleaſing, Phil.</hi> 4. 18. and (in another forme) <hi>Well-pleaſed, (Heb.</hi> 13. 21.) both in reference to Free-almes, and deeds of Nobleſt-charity.</p>
            <p>So then the Apoſtles meaning is, that we muſt not only try, approve and practiſe thoſe things, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly may be pleaſing to God in ſome low degree, ſuch things as ſet as a ſtep beyond his diſpleaſure; but we muſt ſearch and doe thoſe things, which give him higheſt content, and cary us furtheſt into his favour. Things which come up to the exacteſt rule and beare trueſt proportion to the <hi>Standards</hi> of truth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
            <p>Take all gathered into this briefe Propoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is the duty of the Children of light diligently to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>try (and having by tryall found out, to) approve and Practiſe, what is beſt-pleaſing and moſt contentfull to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It did not ſatisfie holy <hi>David</hi> to be kept from <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſinnes,</hi> and to be innocent from the <hi>Great tranſgreſſion, unleſſe the words of his mouth and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of his heart might be acceptable in the ſight of the Lord, his ſtrength and his Redeemer, Pſal.</hi> 19. 14. How deſirous was he, to have his actions accepted, who could not beare it, that a word or a thought of his, ſhould miſſe of acceptation? The Apoſtle inferres this duty upon the whole matter of our Goſpel-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, <hi>Heb. 12. 28. Wherefore we receiving a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113433:5"/> which cannot be ſhaken, let us have Grace whereby we may ſerve him acceptably, with reverence and Godly feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Greater love cals for greater care. And while God (which ſhould pleaſe us fully) gives us mercies, which cannot be ſhaken, we ſhould be ſteddy in our purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, fully, to pleaſe God. <hi>Enoch</hi> the <hi>ſecond Saint</hi> by name, and the <hi>ſeventh Man</hi> from <hi>Adam,</hi> was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Earth to Heaven, <hi>that he ſhould not ſee death.</hi> But what had this man done while he lived upon the earth, which moved the Lord to diſpence with that Great Statute of Heaven (which in our reading was diſpenc'd with but once more) <hi>It is appointed for all men once to die, (Heb.</hi> 9. 27.) The text anſwers, <hi>Before his tranſlation, he had this teſtimony, that he pleaſed God.</hi> By whoſe hands theſe letters Teſtimoniall were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, is not written; whether this was the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Man or of God, or of both is not written, but a Teſtimony he had, <hi>That he pleaſed God.</hi> Were there none before that age who had this Teſtimony? Yes, <hi>Abel</hi> pleaſed God ſo much, that man could not endure he ſhould live; But <hi>Enoch</hi> pleaſed God ſo much, that God could not endure he ſhould dye. Though the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> could not be confident of <hi>Enochs</hi> priviledge; Not to be uncloathed, but cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed upon; That his Mortality might be ſwallowed up of Life, yet hee was as diligent in <hi>Enoch's</hi> duty, (2 <hi>Cor. 5. 10.) We labour</hi> (as covetous men for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or ambitious ſpirits for Honour, ſuch are the reaches of the Originall, we labour) <hi>that whether pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or abſent, we may be accepted with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Title in the text tels us, we cannot goe leſſe,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113433:6"/> then ſuch an accurate care to pleaſe him: He is <hi>our Lord.</hi> If Servants muſt <hi>be ſo obedient to their owne earthly Maſters, as to pleaſe them well in all things, Tit.</hi> 2. 9. How ſhould we pleaſe our Maſter, who is in heaven, and who is Lord of earth and heaven. Man is apt enough to pleaſe, where he hath dependancies, and ſtrives to be accepted, where much is to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. All preferments and offices are in the guift and at the diſpoſe of this Lord. <hi>Promotion comes neither from the Eaſt nor from the Weſt, nor from the South; But God is the Judge, he putteth downe one, and ſetteth up another, Pſal.</hi> 75. 6, 7. When King <hi>Herod</hi> was high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpleaſed, with them of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> they came with one accord unto him and deſired Peace, becauſe their Country was nouriſhed by the Kings Country, (<hi>Act.</hi> 12. 20.) Our Country is nouriſhed by CHRISTS country, Heaven feeds the Earth, and can we live with a diſpleaſed Chriſt?</p>
            <p>And as our rewards and comforts come from him now, ſo hereafter, muſt our judgement. That's the Apoſtles reaſon 2 <hi>Cor. 5. 9. 10. Wherefore we labour, that whether preſent or abſent we may be accepted with him; for wee muſt all appeare before the judgement Seate of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>&amp;c. Many</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) ſeeke the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers favour, but every mans judgement is of the Lord, Prov.</hi> 29. 26. Why hath the Rulers ſo many ſuitors for his favour? Is it not becauſe the judgement of inferiours proceeds from him? <hi>Salomon</hi> denies not this, while he affirmes that every mans judgement is of the Lord, but teaches us to ſeeke Gods favour chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both, becauſe hee can over-rule the Rulers heart to give a right judgement, and will himſelf give the laſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113433:6"/> judgement (from which there lyes no appeale) to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man.</p>
            <p>Againe, that which is acceptable to the Lord is moſt excellent in it ſelf. Low things may pleaſe men in high place. <hi>And that which is highly eſteemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst men, is an abomination to the Lord, (Luk.</hi> 16. 15). But whatſoever is highly eſteemed of the Lord, hath a reall worth in it. That muſt be rich and pure wine which pleaſes the quickeſt palate, and that an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Picture which pleaſes the skilfulleſt eye. It is argument enough, that a thing is good, when it pleaſes the <hi>Chiefe Good.</hi> Some men are ſo bad, that the worſt things pleaſe them beſt. God is ſo good that nothing but good can pleaſe him; and, becauſe he is the Chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt good, therefore the better any thing is, the more it pleaſes him. We cannot deſire a ſtronger or a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler ground of reaſon induſtriouſly to pleaſe another, then this aſſurance, that we cannot pleaſe him with any thing, which is not Honourable in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>This point caries a reproofe in it againſt foure ſorts of men.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſuch as Practiſe what they have not proved or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> tryed. The Apoſtles method is, <hi>Firſt to Prove all things then hold fast that which is good, 1 Theſ.</hi> 5. 21. And the reaſon why many doe not hold faſt that which is good is, becauſe they did not firſt Prove it. <hi>David</hi> could not march in <hi>Sauls</hi> Armour, for he had not aſſayed it. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 9. In this ſence a man may practiſe a truth too ſoone. And they who practiſe it thus ſoone, will not practiſe it long. How many thouſands practiſing truths which they never tryed, have let them goe, when themſelves were tryed. The not rooting of Truth in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113433:7"/> the underſtanding (as well as not in the affections) is a root of Apoſtacy. What we doe upon the reaſon or command of men, will not beare up againſt the reaſon and command of men. The Treble Turne which this Kingdome felt in a few yeares (not many yeares ſince) from Popery to Proteſtantiſme, from <hi>This</hi> to <hi>That,</hi> from <hi>That</hi> to <hi>This</hi> againe, is a proofe, to this day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waylable, of their unſteddineſſe, who Practiſe what they have not Proved.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch are reproved by this Truth, who pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> what they approve not, which may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood two wayes; Firſt Conſcience being againſt it: ſecondly, Conſcience not being ſatisfied or affected with it. Carnall men doe good as Godly men doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, (<hi>Rom. 7. 15) They allow not of the good they doe.</hi> Vaine-glory and the applauſe of men, made the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies</hi> frequent in Prayer, Faſting, and Almeſ-deeds, the ſpiritualneſſe and holineſſe of which Duties they ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted not (<hi>Math.</hi> 6.) Covetouſneſſe cauſed the <hi>Siche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> to ſubmit to Circumciſion, their conſciences were not taken with it. The argument which moved them, lay in the Cattle and earthly goods of <hi>Iacobs</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, not in the heavenly Good, which that Covenant ſealed and aſſured from God, <hi>Gen. 34. 17. Shall not their Cattle, and their ſubſtance and every beaſt of theirs, be ours, Verſ</hi> 25. How many are daily led by feare of cenſures from men, by deſire of concurrence and compliance with men, by the ſway and ſtreame of Times, at the meere appointment and command of Man, to doe or forbeare thoſe things at which their Conſciences never ſcrupled, with which their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences never cloſed? I will leave but two words with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113433:7"/> this Generation. Firſt, they who doe good things, which they approve not, ſhall never be approved by God for doing them. Secondly, God will ranke and reckon them among evil-doers, who have done good, which they approved not.</p>
            <p>3.<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, they fall under the reproof of this point, who will <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> not Practiſe what, or who practiſe contrary to what their underſtandings, have proved or tried, &amp; their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences have approved or liked. Not to doe the good we ſee and allow, or to doe croſſe to what we ſee and allow, are both abominations to the Lord. <hi>The wrath of God is revealed from heaven against their unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, who (thus) hold the truth in unrighteouſneſse, Rom.</hi> 1. 18. Truth is not only free, but it makes thoſe who receive it, free. Woe to thoſe who make bonds for truth, who impriſon and enſlave it, who violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hold downe truth, leſt it ſhould exerciſe due do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and command over their actions. Such is their caſe who ſmother the light of cleare Principles received, and know better, then they dare or have a will to appeare and doe. <hi>Thou knoweſt his will</hi> (ſo the ſame Apoſtle chides them too) <hi>and approveſt the things that that are more excellent, being inſtructed out of the law, Rom. 2. 18. Thou therefore that teacheſt another, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt thou not thy ſelfe? &amp;c. As that man is happie, who condemneth not himſelfe in that thing which hee alloweth,</hi> (by a ſcandalous practiſe of it) <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 22. So happie is that man who condemneth not himſelf, in that thing which he alloweth, by a ſcandalous neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of it. As ſome Hereticks, ſo this ſort of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites are Self-condemners. While a Heretick would logically juſtifie his falſe opinion, and while theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113433:8"/> hypocrites will not practically follow their true opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, they both really (though neither of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionally) condemne their own perſons.</p>
            <p>The fourth ſort which this Point deales with, faile <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> in the object of their acceptation. Their care is not to prove and find out what is acceptable to God, but what is acceptable to men. Men-pleaſers they are, not God-pleaſers; they ſtudy what is like to take with the world, not what is given as the mind of CHRIST. The <hi>greateſt number</hi> would faine pleaſe thoſe who are <hi>great in Dignity,</hi> and ſometime they who are <hi>great in dignity</hi> will induſtriouſly pleaſe the <hi>greateſt Number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When</hi> Herod <hi>had killed</hi> Iames <hi>the Brother of the Lord with the Sword, becauſe he ſaw it pleaſed the Iewes,</hi> he proceeded further to take <hi>Peter</hi> alſo (<hi>Act.</hi> 12. 3.) He cares not to ſpill the blood of an innocent, ſo he may pleaſe the humour of the multitude. The ſinne is neere of the ſame ſtature, whether <hi>Great men</hi> ſinne to pleaſe <hi>many,</hi> or <hi>many</hi> ſin to pleaſe thoſe who are <hi>Great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> (I grant) <hi>pleaſed all men in all things, 1 Cor.</hi> 10. 33. and concludes (<hi>Rom. 15. 2.) Let every one of us pleaſe his neighbour.</hi> It is our duty to doe ſo, but take the limitation which followes; <hi>for his good to Edification.</hi> We may pleaſe men to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie them, but not to flatter them, to do them good, not to make our ſelves Great or rich: So the holy Apoſtle explaines his <hi>Noble Paraſitiſme, I pleaſe all men in all things, not ſeeking mine owne profit, but the profit of many, that they may be ſaved.</hi> All man-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but that whereby we profit thoſe we pleaſe, is diſpleaſing unto God. And the profit he meanes is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113433:8"/> not either in filling or ſaving their purſes, but in ſaving their Soules. Any other man-pleaſing he diſclaimes, as having no allowance at all from God, (1 <hi>Theſ. 2. 3, 4.) Our exhoration was not of deceit, &amp;c: but as we were allowed of God to be put in truſt with the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, not as pleaſing men but God, who tryeth the hearts: Nor at any time uſed we flattering words, as ye know</hi> (you muſt have heard them had we uſed them) <hi>nor a cloake of Covetouſneſſe</hi> (that I confeſſe is beyond your ſight, Covetouſneſſe is a cloſe ſinne, and the intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it cloſer, but) <hi>God is witneſſe, nor of men ſought we glory, &amp;c.</hi> Glory or gaine, profit or praiſe, are the uſuall provocations to ſuch flattery. He that is above the bayt, ſhall not fall into the ſnare.</p>
            <p>I have foure things to ſay to theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they who ſinfully endeavour acceptation with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> men, ſhall not long be accepted with men. Men-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers run into greateſt diſpleaſure with men. None find ſuch unwelcome concluſions, as they who have condiſcended in ſpeech or action to the loweſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyances. When Cardinall <hi>Wolſey</hi> ſaw himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by <hi>that King,</hi> hee ſayd; <hi>If I had laboured to pleaſe and ſerve God, as I have done to ſerve and pleaſe my Prince, I had not bin thus caſt off and forſaken.</hi> Many ſuch wrackt and weather-beaten wretches, will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine at laſt, that they too much ſought and pleaſed themſelves with the Faire-weather and warme Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch uſually prove unacceptable to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> After <hi>Achitophel</hi> had ſinfully ingratiated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with <hi>Abſolom,</hi> to betray <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> with the Scribes and Phariſies to betray CHRIST, they both
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113433:9"/> fell out with themſelves and ended their lives under the disfavour of their own Conſciences. How many, having (to regaine their loſt reputation with men) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the truth, have preſently bin renounced by their own hearts, and could never get a good word, or a good looke from them againe: And they who have not found that quarrell endleſſe, have taken ſoare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges upon Themſelves, and could not recover their peace, till they had acknowledged and bewayled their owne cowardiſe. <hi>Cranmer,</hi> puts his right-hand into the fire, which had ſubſcribed his Recantation. And <hi>Iewel</hi> mournes in <hi>Germany</hi> for a ſubſcription he made in <hi>England</hi> to the Popiſh Inquiſitors. <hi>The hypocrites hope ſhall be cut off</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bildad, Iob</hi> 8. 14.) the word ſignifies alſo extreame Loathing, and Abominating; which implyes his hope ſhall be ſo cut off, that hee ſhall be a Loathing to himſelfe. It is an affliction (and in ſome caſes a very great one) to be Loathed by other men, but it is a farre greater for a man to be loathed by his owne Soule.</p>
            <p>There is a twofold Self-loathing; Firſt, of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſecondly, of Deſperation; this latter is there portion: And that's as black as the ſuburbs of hell, and lyes but one ſtep from the regions of everlaſting darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſuch diſpleaſe Chriſt ſo much, that hee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> diſcards them his ſervice, <hi>Gal. 1. 10. Doe I now perſwade men, or God; Paul</hi> preached of God, not to God: God is above mans Rhetorick, or perſwaſions, why then doth he ſay, <hi>Doe I perſwade men, or God?</hi> His meaning is, doe I perſwade the things of men or of God, doe I perſwade you to heare and obey Men or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113433:9"/> God: Or (as our late Annotators) doe we make faith to men, or ſeeke to endeare our ſelves to men. The next words of the Text give us this gloſſe, doe <hi>I ſeeke to pleaſe men?</hi> Why <hi>Paul,</hi> what danger or dammage if thou hadſt? yes, very great: <hi>For if I yet pleaſed men, I ſhould not be the ſervant of Christ. No man can ſerve two Maſters, vnleſſe their will and commands be one.</hi> It is beſt for man when his will (in reference to the object) is melted into Gods; yet God and ſome men are never, God and no man are alwaies (in this ſence) <hi>Monothelites:</hi> And therefore they who reſolve to pleaſe men alwaies, ſhall be ſure to pleaſe God but ſeldome, if at all. <hi>The two Witneſſes tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them that dwelt upon the earth, Rev.</hi> 11. 10. How could two torment millions? What were the racks or engines upon which they held the world in paine? It was their plaine-ſpeaking and plaine-doing what was acceptable to the Lord. They who will <hi>follow them,</hi> or, are <hi>now Acting</hi> them, ſhall ſure enough, anger all wicked men who dwell upon the earth, and poſſibly (in ſome things) ſome of them, who are godly too. Truth puts the world into a rage, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 1. Every rule of duty is a <hi>Band</hi> of ſlavery, and every holy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell a Cord, which they will breake a ſunder, if they can, and caſt away from them. How then ſhall they pleaſe God, who are ſtudious to pleaſe ſuch men? And as All holy truths put all the world (whether their ſound comes) into a rage: So ſome truths are ſo holy, that they may put ſome Churches, or ſome of the Churches into a rage. Every good man is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in a frame to receive all that is Good. How then ſhall they pleaſe God, who are reſolved to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113433:10"/> doe or ſay no more then pleaſes all good men?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, while we ſeeke to be accepted with men, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> our owne hearts are ſtopt from much ſeeking or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding acceptation with God. CHRIST puts an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame difficulty, if not an impoſſibility upon it, <hi>Ioh. 5. 44. How can yee beleeve, which receive honour one of another, and ſeeke not the Honour, which commeth of God only.</hi> It is poſſible to receive honour both from God and man for the ſame thing. <hi>Only of God,</hi> doth not exclude the honour <hi>of Men,</hi> but teaches us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to doe our duty, when honour comes from God <hi>only.</hi> The meaning of Chriſt is, unleſſe (though wee ſleight not honour from men) we can reſt ſatisfied with honour from God <hi>only, We cannot</hi> (which is our hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of God) beleeve him. They never give God cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit who are in Love with credit from the world. Or if Chriſt gaine faith in the hearts of ſuch, yet he looſes their Profeſſion of him, with the mouth. Among the chiefe Rulers many beleeved on Chriſt, but they did not confeſſe him (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 12. 42.) And this reaſon is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; <hi>For they loved the Praiſe of men, more then the praiſe of God.</hi> That man who loves the praiſe of God, but as much, as he loves the praiſe of men, loves it leſſe. Seeing there is nothing more unequall then this equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Where the obligation is unequall we cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our duty by making our payments equall. If then, it could be ſuppoſed, that a man did gradually love the praiſe of men, no more then he loves the praiſe of men, yet really he loves it more. And when once a mans affections are thus warme after the world, how cold and unactive is he after JESVS CHRIST. He muſt have the ſmiles and embraces, the good word and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113433:10"/> acceptation of men, though he run the hazard of his acceptation with the Lord.</p>
            <p>I have done with matter of reproofe. This poynt will alſo informe and give us an account of the reaſon why the ſervants of Chriſt ſtand ſo ſtrictly upon their Termes with the world, even till ſome call it <hi>vaine preciſeneſſe</hi> &amp; others <hi>wilfull ſtubborneſſe.</hi> When <hi>Pharaoh</hi> came to the loweſt termes of a compoſition with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> about the departure of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of Egypt; <hi>Goe yee ſerve the Lord, onely let your flockes and your heards be ſtayed, let your little ones alſo goe with you:</hi> will <hi>Moſes</hi> yeeld to this? No, <hi>Our Cattle alſo ſhall goe with us, there ſhall not an hoofe be left behind us.</hi> Was not this obſtinacy in <hi>Moſes?</hi> Why was he thus rigid and peremptory with ſo great a King? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if <hi>Moſes</hi> had bin to pleaſe himſelfe onely in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, he had accepted his owne peace and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of <hi>Iſrael</hi> on thoſe or eaſier termes to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah,</hi> but he had a God to pleaſe whoſe right he could not give away in the leaſt thing. Which he clearely intimates in the next words. <hi>There ſhall not an hoofe be left behind: for thereof muſt we take to ſerve the Lord our God; And we know not with what we muſt ſerve the Lord untill we come thither.</hi> Exod. 10. 26. As if <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> had ſaid, if we had nothing to doe with our cattle but only to worke or eat them, we might (poſſibly) hearken to thy motion. And rather leave our beaſts to thee, then to live an houre longer within the reach of ſo cruel a beaſt as thou; But the Lord hath uſe of our cattle as well as we; Thereof muſt we take to ſerve the Lord our God. And we will not take upon us to part out his portion here, we expect direction
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113433:11"/> from him, there; We may bring what he likes not, therefore he ſhall take his choice of all, a hoofe ſhall not ſtay behind. I will not <hi>bate an ace,</hi> or <hi>looſe a ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. The lips of the righteous know what is acceptable, Prov.</hi> 10. 32. To know is the worke of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to ſpeak is the worke of the lips: how then ſaith <hi>Salomon, That the lips of the righteous know?</hi> There is a great affinity betweene Reaſon and Speech; and therefore the lips which are an organ of Speech, are honoured with the work of the underſtanding. Or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a righteous man hath much true knowledge; therefore his lips are ſayd to know (as <hi>Davids</hi> hands are ſaid to underſtand and hee to governe by the underſtanding of his hands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 72. His hands underſtood more then the heads of ordinary Princes) in this ſence (I ſay) <hi>the lips of a righteous man are ſaid to know.</hi> And among all Objects of knowledge, this, he eyther doth or deſires to know moſt, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>What is acceptable.</hi> And becauſe hee is ſo much skil'd in this Point, he will runne all hazards to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it, and doe what is acceptable to the Lord. The Holy Apoſtles put this queſtion to the Vote of their profeſſed Enemies, <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God to hearken unto you more then unto God, judge yee. Act.</hi> 4. 19. The ſervants of Chriſt know very well what the concernements are of man-pleaſing. They know favour, and honour, and riches, and reſpects come in at that doore, and they are not ignorant of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe things, nor yet ſo ſtoicall as not to deſire to enjoy them; They know alſo what the frownes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of men are, what ſtormes clouded browes portend: they are very ſenſible of it, what is to be ſlighted, what to be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113433:11"/> poore, what to be ſcourged, what to be impriſoned: and they are not ſo ſtoicall as not to deſire to avoid theſe things. Chriſt himſelfe (according to his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) was not a thirſt for a bitter cup, but prayed thrice, <hi>Father if it be posſible, let this cup paſſe from me.</hi> Only that which ſatisfied CHRIST, ſatisfies them. Not our will but thy will be done. And upon that title, they thinke all men ſhould be of their mind, and are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be of that mind, though all men are againſt them; <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto you more then unto God, judge yee;</hi> we beleeve you are of our mind: However we reſolve to be of that mind, though you vote againſt it, for that's our duty. <hi>We ought to obey God rather then men,</hi> Chap. 5. 29.</p>
            <p>Then, let the ſtrength of your endeavours run out in ſeeking and doing what is acceptable to the Lord. Pray continually, <hi>Lord, let us have Grace, whereby wee may ſerve thee acceptably.</hi> Let nothing be acceptable to us, which is not to the Lord. Let us reckon all our walkings, wandrings, which are not in pathes pleaſing to him. Reſolve to live unacceptably to <hi>all,</hi> rather then unacceptably to <hi>One.</hi> As we ſhould ſay, let God be true and All men Lyars; So let God be pleaſed, and all men diſpleaſed. <hi>Who art thou</hi> (dares any man appeare and ſhew his head upon this chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge) <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt be affraid of a man that ſhall dye, and of the Sonne of man that ſhall be made as the graſſe, and forgetteſt</hi> (to pleaſe) <hi>the Lord thy Maker, that ſtretched forth the heavens, and layd the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the earth, &amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 51. 12, 13. Conſider</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is a great honour to Chriſt, when all ſtudy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113433:12"/> to pleaſe him. It is the glory of Princes that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrive to be accepted with them, and to find favour in their eyes. We cannot but eſteeme (or at leaſt pretend to eſteeme) him much, whom we labour to pleaſe much: And ſuch as we eſteeme highly of, we are ready not only to pleaſe but to humour. Chriſt ſhould have this honour from all the Saints: an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectarion to pleaſe him is their duty: Yea (with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence be it received) it is their duty to humour him. Not that there is any imaginable humour in Chriſt, all whoſe commands are bottom'd upon infinit rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But my meaning is only this: our care to pleaſe Chriſt ſhould bee exact and curious, and that then we honour him moſt, when we not only doe thoſe things which cary the light of a cleare neceſſity, or the great things of the Goſpell, but thoſe alſo, which moſt looke upon, but as (<hi>Minucia's</hi>) ſmall matters, the tything of Mint and Cummin, formes, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and (as it were) curioſities in Religion. To prove and practiſe what is acceptable to the Lord in the leaſt things, gives greateſt honour to the Lord. Our obedience is the more, where the duty is leſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is a great priviledge to be accepted <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> with Chriſt. The Lord appointed <hi>Aaron</hi> to weare a <hi>Golden plate upon his Mitre,</hi> with this inſcription, HOLINES TO THE LORD. And this muſt be upon <hi>Aarons</hi> forehead, that hee might beare the iniquity of the Holy things which the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould hallow in all their holy guifts; And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon given was this, <hi>That they might be accepted before the Lord.</hi> As if the Lord had ſaid, This ſhall be <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> honour, above all the Nations of the earth. They
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113433:12"/> ſhall be accepted before the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28. 36. This was <hi>Moſes</hi> Prayer for the Tribe of <hi>Levi. Bleſſe Lord his ſubſtance, and accept the worke of his hands, Deut.</hi> 33. 11. When wrath was growne higheſt and hotteſt againſt <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> this Charter was recalled. <hi>When they Paſt I will not heare their cry, and when they offer burnt offerings and an oblation I will not accept them,</hi> Ier. 14. 12. <hi>They ſacrifice Fleſh for the ſacrifice of mine offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and eate it, but the Lord accepteth it not, Hoſ.</hi> 8. 13. They may fill themſelves, and make merry with their Sacrifices, but the Lord will not taſt a bit, or give them a <hi>Thanke,</hi> for all the coſt they beſtow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his holy Feaſts. <hi>To what purpoſe is the multitude of your Sacrifices unto me ſaith the Lord, I am full of the burnt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> offerings of Rams and of the fat of fed beaſts,</hi> Iſa. 1. 11. <hi>The Lord was full,</hi> not as a man is full, with feeding plentifully upon meat he likes, but full, as a man is cloyed with the very ſight of meat he loathes; ſo the next words expound it. <hi>I delight not in the blood of Bullocks or of Rams.</hi> When God ſayth to a People, to what purpoſe are your Prayers, your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings, your faſtings? I am full of them, It is an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument he accepts none of them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the comfort which ariſes from the ſence <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of our acceptation with Chriſt is unſpeakable. <hi>Iacob</hi> was much comforted in a probability, that his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau</hi> would accept him. <hi>I will</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>appeaſe him with the preſent, that goeth before me, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward I will ſee his face, peradventure he will accept of me, Gen.</hi> 32. 20. It was ſome comfort to him to have but a ground of hope, that the clouds which had bin ſo long gathered in the brow of <hi>Eſau</hi> would ſhortly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113433:13"/> diſſolve<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that he might enjoy the ſhine of a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed looke, from his angry, revengefull Brother.</p>
            <p>How earneſtly doth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> beſpeake, yea beg Prayers, that the ſervice which he had for <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, might be accepted with the Saints, Rom.</hi> 15. 31. It is no ſmall comfort to have a place in the hearts of the Saints. The good word and approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one Good man, weighed more with <hi>Paul</hi> then the commendation of all the world which was not ſuch. There is a Teſtimony from a third hand, which is a richer treaſure then this. <hi>Paul</hi> found it ſo, and he could not conceale it, 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 12. Our rejoycing is this, the teſtimony of our Conſcience, &amp;c.</hi> Acceptance with the men of the world (while we keepe a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) is a great mercy; But as to be accepted with the Saints is more deſirable then with all other men; So to be accepted in our own Conſciences is more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable then with all the Saints. <hi>To pleaſe and heare well with the Saint within us, is better then to pleaſe, and heare well, with the Saints without us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet the Point in hand ſhewes us a higher conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then theſe. For as the teſtimony of God againſt us is more terrible then that of our own hearts (1 <hi>Ioh. 3. 20.) If our heart condemne us, God is greater then our hearts and knoweth all things:</hi> and therefore knoweth more evill by us, and every evill more, then our own hearts doe. So the teſtimony of God for us, is more comfortable then that of our own hearts. If our hearts acquit and accept of us, God is greater then our hearts, and knowing all things, He knoweth more good by us, and every good more, then our owne hearts doe. Who can expreſſe how ſweet it is to heare well with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113433:13"/> God, and to receive this Teſtimony, that wee pleaſe him? When Conſcience ſpeakes us faire, we have Peace; but when Gods ſpeakes us faire and gives us an <hi>Euge</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om heaven, <hi>Well done good and faithfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> wee have peace that paſſeth all underſtanding, and joyes which are unſpeakable and glorious. <hi>A good Conſcience is a continuall feast,</hi> but this is <hi>hidden Manna,</hi> upon which the Saints eſpecially feed fat, <hi>when the Fig-tree doth not bloſsome, and when there is no fruit in the Vines, when the labour of the Olive failes, and the Fields yeeld no meat, when the Flock ſhall be cut off from the fold, and there ſhall be no Herd in the ſtalls:</hi> Yea when we are at fulleſt Tables, this is the ſauce in our diſh and the ſugar in our Cup, <hi>Goe thy way</hi> (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>eate thy bread with joy, and drinke thy wine with a merry heart</hi> (why, what's the matter?) <hi>For God now accepteth thy works. Let thy garments be alwayes white, and let thy head lack no oyntment, live joyfully with the Wife whom thou lovest all the dayes of thy life, &amp;c:</hi> Ioy is ſhed into all the motions and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his life, who is, and knoweth that he is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord.</p>
            <p>This may be cleared further in three Particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe if we are once accepted with Chriſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we are in his Bookes for ever. Creatures are full of changes; And are apt to vary their aſpects every day. Now they ſmile upon us and anon they frowne; now they applaud, anon they diſlike; This day we may be accepted with them, and the next day reprobates. One day the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſing <hi>Hoſannah</hi> to Chriſt, and will force him to a throne, ſhortly after they cry out <hi>Crucifie</hi> him, and nayle him to a Croſſe. In the ſame City
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113433:14"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> with <hi>Barnabas</hi> (being called Gods in the likeneſſe of men) had almoſt bin Sacrificed to, and <hi>Paul</hi> being ſuppoſed unworthy to live amongſt men, was really ſtoned, almoſt to death. The affections of men alter as much as their condition. Only God never alters his opinion of any man; No <hi>Ziba</hi> ſhall ever be able to accuſe us out of the favour of the King of heaven. God never rejects where or whom he hath accepted. Hee never changes his correſpondence. Once a friend and alwaies a friend. Yea he is pleaſed with his, while he manifeſts a fatherly diſpleaſure againſt them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt can command our acceptance in the hearts of men, when to pleaſe him, we venture the diſpleaſure of men. <hi>Daniel</hi> (chap. 1. 8, 9.) <hi>purpoſed in his heart, that he would not defile himſelfe with the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings meat, nor with the Wine which hee dranke. Now God had brought</hi> Daniel <hi>into favour and tender love with the Prince of the Eunuchs.</hi> Carnall policy might have prompted <hi>Daniel</hi> thus, Meats in their owne nature are indifferent, and the reaſon upon which the command of their diſtinction is grounded may (poſſibly) be of an inferiour Nature to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of mine and my brethrens lives, which, as things ſtand, depends on the favour of the great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the Court of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Theſe or the like thoughts made no impreſſion upon his ſpirit: but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the honour of God, and the credit of the <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Religion muſt have bin ſhaken by his yeelding to <hi>Gentiliſme</hi> in the leaſt degree; therefore hee reſolves to run all hazards rather then this. But the Story tels us, how the Lord calmed and meek'ned the Spirit of the Prince of the Eunuchs towards <hi>Daniel,</hi> inſomuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113433:14"/> that he endangers his owne head to the King, rather then he will force the conſcience of a Captive. And therefore winkes at his under Officer diſpencing with the rigour of that hard Law. Who would not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in his heart to keepe cloſe to the will of Chriſt, when Chriſt can thus command the wills of men, and cauſe them to yeeld in curteſie, when we will not yeeld for conſcience. It is at once the comfort and the priviledge of the Saints, that they ſerve a King who rules the Spirits of men, as well as their Bodies. <hi>When his people were few in number yea very few and ſtrangers in the Land, when they went from one Nation to another, from one Kingdome to another people. He ſuffered no man to doe them wrong, but reproved even Kings for their ſakes. Pſal.</hi> 105. 12, 13, 14. Many had (as we ſay) an a king tooth at the people of God, their fingers itcht to be a dealing with them. And what hindred? The text gives us foure advantages that the world had of them. Firſt, they were few; ſecondly, very few; thirdly, ſtrangers; fourthly, unſetled? what hindred them? It was the Lord: Hee reſtrained the ſpirits of Princes, and the madneſſe of the people. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny offered and attempted, but the Lord ſuffered no man to do them wrong. Hence the Lord that he might encourage the <hi>Iewes</hi> after they were ſafe in <hi>Canaan,</hi> to come up freely to the place of his worſhip, gives them this aſſurance. <hi>No man ſhall deſire thy Land when thou ſhalt goe up to appeare before the Lord thy God thrice in the yeare (Exod.</hi> 24. 34.) God can keepe not only hands from ſpoyling, but hearts from deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. And as the <hi>concupiſcible appetite</hi> in man is under his command, ſo alſo is the <hi>iracible.</hi> He can ſtay an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113433:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113433:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113433:16"/> and wrath as well as covetouſneſſe and deſire. <hi>When a mans wayes pleaſe God he maketh even his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to be at Peace with him. (Prov.</hi> 16. 7.) why then ſhould we diſpleaſe God to avoid the warres and emnities of men? <hi>Auſtin</hi> brings in ſome excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their compliances with the ſinfull cuſtomes of thoſe times, in drinking Healths, thus. <hi>Great Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deus qui te videt, per ejus amorem ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> non vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, ipſe tibi gratiam etiam illorum dabit qui te, ut plus hiberis vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur cogere. <hi>Serm. 2. do de Temp.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>urged us to it, and it was at the Kings banquet, where they judged of Loyalty by Luxury, and put us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this election, drinke or dye, The not drinking of a health had bin our death.</hi> He gives many anſwers to theſe cowards, but this eſpecially to the preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>That God, who ſees that for love to him, thou wouldeſt not conforme to their drunken cuſtomes, will give thee favour in their eyes, who thus threatned thee to drinke.</hi> This argument holds in the point of Faith and worſhip, as well as of manners. When God ſees we will not pollute our conſciences to pleaſe men, he alwayes can and often doth make men, if not pleaſed with us, yet at peace with us. <hi>He</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Rom. 14. 18.) that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt is acceptable to God, and approved of men.</hi> God and good men approve the ſame things and perſons. And God can cauſe evill men who approve not the ſame things, yet to approve the ſame perſons. Even as he often makes thoſe <hi>who feare not God contrary to all men (1 Theſ.</hi> 2. 15.) They ſhall not long pleaſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or bad, who care not to pleaſe God. And they often pleaſe the bad (not that their hearts are ſuited but over-ruled to them) who will doe goed, leſt they ſhould diſpleaſe the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Chriſts</hi> acceptance ſets us above the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113433:16"/> of the world. How low a thing is credit with men, when once the ſoule hath found credit with God. <hi>No man</hi> (ſaith CHRIST) <hi>having drunke old Wine, ſtraightway deſireth new, for he ſaith, the old is better. (Luke</hi> 5. 39.) The Favour of God is old Wine, even as old as Eternity. They who have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted how gracious the Lord is, can never hunger or thirſt after grace in the eyes of men. And therefore as the three children in <hi>Daniel</hi> told <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> (chap. 3. 17. 18.) <hi>Our God whom we ſerve is able to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us from the burning furnace, and he will deliver us out of thy hand O King; But if not, be it knowne unto thee O King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip the golden Image which thou haſt ſet up.</hi> They knew they ſhould be above fire, when they were in the midſt of it. Thus the children of light ſay unto this day; Our God whom we ſerve is able to keepe us out of the fire of mens diſpleaſure and indignation, and to cauſe the light of their countenance to ſhine upon us. But if not, we will not comply to worſhip any Image of mans erecting; for wee are above the rage and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of men, while we are filled with it. When <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> danced with all his might before the Arke, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Sauls</hi> daughter looking out at a window <hi>deſpiſed him in her heart (2 Sam.</hi> 6. 16.) and at the 20.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe jeeres him with her tongue: <hi>How glorious was the King of Iſrael to day, &amp;c.</hi> But was <hi>Davids</hi> zeale coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or his ſpirit troubled becauſe he miſſed acceptance with his Queen in that Holy ſervice? Nothing leſſe; hee deſpiſes that ſhame: and <hi>David ſaid unto</hi> Michal <hi>(verſ. 21.) It was before the Lord, which choſe me before thy Father and all his houſe,  therefore will I play be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113433:17"/> the Lord, and I will yet be more vile then thus, and will be baſe in mine owne eyes, &amp;c.</hi> As if <hi>David</hi> had ſayd; <hi>Madam,</hi> thoſe higher raptures and actings of my Devotion, were never intended to pleaſe thee, but God: It was <hi>before the Lord,</hi> not <hi>before Thee</hi> or the <hi>Court Ladies</hi> that I danced; and therefore if this makes me cheape and vile in your eyes, I will yet be more vile. He that really and intendedly honours God, can eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly digeſt diſhonour from the creature. <hi>It is a very ſmall thing that I ſhould be judged of you</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) or of mans judgement, But hee that judgeth me is the Lord (1 Cor.</hi> 4. 3, 4.) that is, Though men doe nothing but judge and cenſure me, yet (with me) their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtands for nothing: The Lords judgement is the judgement I appeale to, and the judgement I muſt ſtand to; <hi>He that judgeth me is the Lord.</hi> He breathes out the ſame Spirit, in his 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Epiſtle. <hi>I trust that you ſhall know, that we are not reprobates</hi> (that is, I doubt not but we ſhall give proofe that we are not rejected of CHRIST, not deſerve to be diſregarded of you.) <hi>Now I pray to God that yet doe no evill, not that we ſhould appeare approved, but that yee ſhould doe that which is honeſt, though we be as reprobates,</hi> Chap. 13. v. 6. 7. As if he had ſaid, I am not in this, projecting for my owne reputation among you, but for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God in your ſalvation, which being once well ſetled and aſſured, I care not much what acceptance my name hath among you, whether I be approved or diſapproved, eſteemed, or ſlighted. <hi>Doe yee approve your ſelves as the Elect of God, and then let me be your Reprobate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a ſpring of comfort ariſes to the Soule and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113433:17"/> makes glad the whole city of God, upon the eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of acceptation with him? When we conſider, that if we are once accepted with him, we ſhall be ſo for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever; That he commands favour from the world for all his Favorites, or lifts them up above the disfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the world; what heart will not be heated up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe conſiderations, ambitiouſly to labour after the acceptance both of his perſon and actions with the Lord.</p>
            <p>And leaſt any ſhould labour in vaine, let me give a few counſels and directions:</p>
            <p>Firſt, get a rule for your worke, a warrant for what <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> you doe. Nothing pleaſes God but what himſelfe appoints. <hi>In vaine doe they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrine the traditions of men. Obedience is better then Sacrifice, and to hearken then the fat of Rams.</hi> He that Sacrificed, under the law, offered up a beaſt, but he that obeyed offer'd up himſelf. To obey God is more then to ſerve him: And he reſpects nothing in all our ſervices, but to ſee himſelf obeyed. <hi>Livia the Empreſſe</hi> being asked, how ſhe had the happineſſe to pleaſe <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſo exactly; Anſwered, I alwayes acted what <hi>Auguſtus</hi> commanded. <hi>I have received of the Lord</hi> (ſayth <hi>Paul) that which alſo I delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, 1 Cor.</hi> 11. 23. And at the 5.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe of the next Chapter; <hi>There are differences of adminiſtrations, but the ſame Lord.</hi> In relation to <hi>This Lord,</hi> we are all fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſervants, and no man anothers Maſter. No man knowes what will pleaſe the Lord, but himſelf. As no man hath bin Gods councellour to direct him what to doe with us; ſo no man can be his Councellor to direct him, what to require of us.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:113433:18"/>
            <p>And if at any time we are in the darke about the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall rule of what he requires. Then wee muſt reſort to the generall Rules. Chiefly, theſe Two:</p>
            <p>Conſider firſt, what is moſt for the glory of God. That Doctrine or Practiſe which lifts up the name of God, muſt needs be related to the will of God; For as God hath made, ſo hee hath written all things for himſelf. His owne honour is his deſigne in his word, as well as in his workes, in what he would have us doe, as well as in what himſelf hath done. All truths ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God. God is the ſpring of truth; nothing flowes from him which is unlike him, or againſt him. To ſerve God is to honour him, and therefore we cannot truly ſerve him in any thing which doth not honour him.</p>
            <p>Conſider ſecondly, what tends moſt to make man holy. Truth in doctrine, and a true way in worſhip purifie both heart and life. <hi>Ye are cleane</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>through the Word which I have ſpoken to you, Ioh.</hi> 15. 3. And he prayes, <hi>Sanctifie them thorough thy truth, thy Word is truth (Ioh.</hi> 17. 17.) That which is pure will make pure. We may read the Nature of many things in their effects: All the ordinances of Worſhip beare this Inſcription, <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord,</hi> and are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to worke <hi>Holineſse in Man.</hi> That which is not ſerviceable to this end, or hath but a ſhew of it, cannot be of Gods appointment.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Direction is this, <hi>In every thing thou</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>doeſt doe thy best.</hi> A little may be acceptable to the Lord, if it be all, and a great deale is not, if wee have more. It is not the quantity but the entireneſſe of what we doe, which pleaſes the Lord. It is a truth in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113433:18"/> all caſes as well as in that of Almes (2 <hi>Cor. 8. 12.) If there be first a willing mind, it is accepted according to that a man hath, and not according to that a man hath not.</hi> But then, whatſoever a man does or gives it muſt be <hi>according to what he hath</hi> (that is, as much as hee hath in his ſtocke for ſuch an end) or elſe it cannot be accepted. The poore Widow caſt in more then all the rich men into the Treaſury (<hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 1, 2, 3.) becauſe though they gave more, yet ſhe gave all; Her all was very little, and their part, was a great deale; yet her little being all, was more then their great deale, being but a part. It is thus in every duty, be it little or much, it muſt be all we have, and the beſt we can. <hi>Curſed be the deceiver which hath in his Flock a male, and voweth and Sacrificeth</hi> (that is, having a Vow upon him, or having vowed to Sacrifice, ſacrificeth) <hi>a corrupt thing, Mal.</hi> 1. 14.</p>
            <p>This direction hath two branches, requiring us to act,</p>
            <p>Firſt, according to the beſt of our ſtrength; The whole man muſt be given up to Chriſt. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and all thy ſoule, and all thy mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, according to the beſt of our light. The Apoſtle prayes for his <hi>Philippians,</hi> that they might <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>things which were excellent</hi> (chap. 1. 10.) or <hi>things which differ:</hi> That is, thoſe things which differ from others in way of excellence; For things differ two wayes. Firſt, in their kind; ſecondly, in their qualities. Light and darkneſſe, Truth and falſhood, good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill differ in their kind. But in the ſecond ſence, light differs from light, truth from truth, one Good from another good. Not only doth Wheat differ from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113433:19"/> Darnel, and Gold from Lead; But wheat from wheat, and gold from gold. Thus, to the point in hand, it is not enough for us, to doe good and not evill, but wee muſt wind up our affections to the higheſt good, and among good things doe the beſt. This the Apoſtles counſel aymes at (<hi>Phil. 4. 8.) Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honest, whatſoever things are just, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe;</hi> that is, (as I conceive) whatſoever things (among thoſe things, which are True, honeſt, juſt, pure, lovely, of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) are moſt vertuous and praiſe-worthy, <hi>thinke on thoſe things, thoſe things doe. Covet earneſtly the best guifts, 1 Cor. 12. 31. chap.</hi> 14. 1. Covet grace above all gifts, and among the Graces covet the beſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 13. God fed the Iſraelites <hi>with the finest of the wheat (Pſal.</hi> 81. 16.) Courſe bread might have kept them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, but he dyeted them to delight as well as to neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. We cannot content Chriſt while we ſet up our reſt in the lower regions of Goſpell-profeſſion. It ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a low ſpirit to ſay, wee will goe no further then will ſerve for Salvation. We muſt ſtudy what will honour Chriſt moſt, not what is the leaſt wherein we may be ſaved. Wee cannot thrive by reſolving upon the cheapeſt way to heaven. While we live on earth we ſhal be in a ſtate of imperfection; but our imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the wayes of Grace, ſhould be like that of Children in nature, who are daily growing up to a fuller ſtature. Hee that labours not to be better, and doe better, drawes a juſt ſuſpition upon himſelf, that he was never good; and that he never did good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113433:19"/> it was good. He that loves wine, doth certainly love the beſt wine; and he who likes what is good, muſt needs like what is better. If the nature of a thing pleaſes us, the perfection of it cannot diſpleaſe: it is moſt acceptable to the Lord, that we ſhould do what we know he moſt accepts.</p>
            <p>Thirdly: Do all in Faith; For <hi>without Faith it is impoſsible to pleaſe God,</hi> Heb. 11. 6. <hi>And whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin, Rom.</hi> 14. 23. By the former text, the works of Infidels and unbeleevers who have no faith at all, are caſt out as unacceptable: But by the latter, that alſo is adjudged unacceptable, which is done by a Beleever without the evidence of a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the word, and a faire aſſurance in his own heart and conſcience: For though a thing have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all evidence in the word, yet if he that doth it, hath no evidence for it in his heart, to him it is ſin. Even as that alſo is ſin, which hath no reall evidence in the word, though our hearts have the higheſt aſſurances about it, and we ready to lay down our lives for it. So then, as that which a man doth according to his conſcience may be a ſin in its ſelf; ſo that which he doth againſt his conſcience, is alwayes a ſin to him. Hee that is not accepted of his owne conſcience in what he doth, cannot be accepted of the Lord in doing it.</p>
            <p>Therefore in things doubtfull to us, we ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forbeare then act; the ſin of Omiſſion lyes in neglecting that which we know to be the will of God, not in a forbearing to act that of which we are really doubtfull whether it be his will or no: And yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuch a not acting comes to be the ſinne of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113433:20"/> if we reſt in not acting, becauſe we are doubting, and are not diligent to have our doubt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, that ſo we may act. If our forbearing to doe a doubtfull duty, or our forbearing a duty, becauſe of ſome doubts about it, be not our burden, it is our ſin. It is poſſible to diſpleaſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the not doing of that, which will diſpleaſe him alſo if we doe it. Our doubts muſt quicken us to induſtry for reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what is to be done; doubting muſt not make us reſolve to ſit down and do nothing. Woe be to thoſe whoſe doubts draw them to ſuch reſolutions. Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is not ſo diſpleaſing to the Lord as our neglect to be taught and come to the knowledge of the truth. Such then muſt pray much, reade much, conferre much, that they may know more. Many (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> prophecying of the latter times) <hi>ſhall run too and fro, and knowledge ſhall be increaſed.</hi> Sedentary men uſually get much knowledge; How them is it ſaid, that theſe ſhall runne too and fro and increaſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. He meanes a running too and fro to inquire and ſearch for knowledge, when we ſtudy men aſwell as Bookes. And run too and fro among men, as the Bee flyes too and fro among the flowers to ſucke ſome honey from every one we light on: He that thus ſearches for wiſdom, is promiſed to find it. And he that cannot learn of his neighbour, may expect to be taught of God. Only take this caution: Be very humble and meeke: God will not take pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ones in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Tutorage. <hi>The meeke will he guide in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the meeke <hi>will he teach his way, (Pſal.</hi> 25. 9.) He cals none but Children into his Schoole. At moſt he hath but a rod for the proud, his leſſons are for the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113433:20"/> the humble. Many think themſelves too wiſe to be taught by men, &amp; moſt men are too wiſe to be taught by God. <hi>I thank thee</hi> (ſaith Chriſt, Matth. 11. 25.) <hi>O Father Lord of Heaven and earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them unto babes;</hi> To them who were ignorant as babes, as alſo, humble and teachable as babes. Upon this account it is that the wiſe and prudent, The lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned clarkes of the world know ſo little of the minde and way of God, for <hi>the uncleane ſhall not paſſe over it, but it ſhall be for thoſe,</hi> (namely the Saints) or <hi>he ſhall be with them,</hi> as a guide to conduct and lead them, and then, <hi>the-way-faring men though fooles ſhall not erre, Iſa.</hi> 35. 8. That is, the ſimpleſt ſo conducted ſhall not miſſe their way; <hi>They that ſeeme to be wiſe in this world, muſt become (ſuch) fooles that they may be wiſe,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 18.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Accept thoſe whom Chriſt accepts;</hi> To accept a perſon whom the Lord accepts, is a thing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry acceptable to the Lord. Our affections and Gods ſhould concenter in the ſame object. <hi>Shouldeſt thou love them which hate the Lord?</hi> ſaid the Prophet to <hi>Iehoſhaphat, 2 Chr.</hi> 19. 2. It is alike unpleaſing to God whether we love and embrace thoſe who hate him, or hate and reject thoſe, whom hee loves. But who are they whom God accepts, and how may we diſtinguiſh them? Take their character from the Apoſtle <hi>Peters</hi> mouth, <hi>Act. 10. 34. 35. Of a truth I perceive, that God is no reſpecter of perſons, but in every Nation, he that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him, and worketh righteouſneſs is accepted with him.</hi> If in every Nation God accepteth ſuch, no Nation ought to, or can ſafely, reject ſuch. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113433:21"/> uſeth the ſame Argument, to move the diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of that age to a forbearance of bitterneſſe one towards another, <hi>Rom. 14. 2, 3. One beleeveth that he may eate all things, another who is weake eateth herbes.</hi> What ſhall they doe in this caſe? may they devour one another, becauſe they cannot eate the ſame meat? Heare his deciſion of this quarrell and the ground of it. <hi>Let not him that eateth, deſpiſe him that eateth not: and let not him which eateth not, judge him that eateth;</hi> (Why may he not?) <hi>for God hath received him.</hi> That is, hee ownes him, and hath admitted him into his Church; therefore doe not thou cenſure and caſt him out, or judge him unworthy to be received in. The ſame Apoſtle exhorts all heartily to be of one mind; and yet injoynes mutuall acceptance (with a <hi>Non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante</hi>) notwithſtanding a great difference, <hi>Phil. 3. 15. 16. Let us therefore, as many as be perfect be thus min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: and if in any thing</hi> (any ſuch thing he meanes, as with which Saint-ſhip may conſiſt) <hi>If in any</hi> (ſuch) <hi>thing, yee be other vſe minded, God ſhall reveale even this unto you.</hi> He doth not ſay, Fire and Sword, Racks and Priſons, raylings and revilings ſhall reveale this to you, but God ſhall reveale even this unto you; Not that ſuch are to wayt for extraordinary immediate ſpeakings and revelations from God: but God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale, by bleſſing and proſpering thoſe meanes which he hath appointed for the reſolving of thoſe who are in doubt, and the reducing of thoſe who are in Error. But what if the Lord neither by himſelf, nor by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth with thoſe meanes, will reveale this to them and ſet them right in their judgements; what muſt we doe in that caſe? The next verſe informes us; <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſse
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113433:21"/> whereto we have attained, let us walke by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame thing. Paul</hi> would have us walke by the ſame rule with them, who come not up to our rule: and to mind the ſame thing with them, who are otherwiſe minded. Here's a practicall myſterie. How can we walke by the ſame rule with thoſe, who have not the ſame rule, and mind the ſame thing with them, who are not of the ſame mind? Yes, we may walke by the ſame rule of love with thoſe, who (in ſome things) have not found the ſame rule of knowledge; and we may mind the ſame thing in Peace, with thoſe who (in ſome things) are not of the ſame mind in opinion. It is ſad to ſee Chriſtians ſo angry about the things they have not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that they quite forget to Love in the things they have attained: And in ſtead of <hi>bearing one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> (difference of judgement among thoſe who feare God and work righteouſneſſe is a burthen I am ſure, and a burthen within the law of that text, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 2) It is ſad (I ſay) that in ſtead of bearing theſe burthens for one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>ſo fulfilling the law of</hi> CHRIST, we ſhould reſolve to make the bearing of them a violation of <hi>the law of Man.</hi> Many (perhaps) are willing to beare ſuch light differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are no burthens; But <hi>Christ</hi> puts us upon this Triall, even to beare that which is a burthen; It is no great matter to ſuffer what we doe not feele, or to beare what comes neere none of our Intereſts. But (as to this point) <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints,</hi> when all they <hi>who feare God and worke Righteouſneſſe</hi> (this counſell aimes at none without that capacity) are accepted by us, though to our own diſadvantage. And by bearing ſuch burthens to the diſadvantage of private Intereſts, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt may gaine no ſmall advantage. Truth may
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113433:22"/> gaine in time, by ſuch a bearing with thoſe who (poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) may be in Error: and Peace among our ſelves will be a preſent gaine towards our common preſervation. And when CHRIST ſees we have learnt humbly to beare with thoſe who (<hi>fearing him and working righteouſneſſe</hi>) are yet <hi>otherwiſe minded:</hi> he (I doubt not) after we have patiently ſuffered one another a while, will eaſe us all of theſe burthens, and by a bright convincing light of Truth make us all of <hi>one Mind.</hi> However, while (on theſe termes) we endeavour a mutuall acceptation among our ſelves, we are all acting what is acceptable to the Lord.</p>
            <p>And that we may according to theſe foure Directions goe on ſo doing, I ſhall provoke your induſtry by three Conſiderations, and ſo an end.</p>
            <p>Firſt, theſe are times wherein a Spirit of Error is gone out into the world. That Prophecy of <hi>Christ</hi> ſeemes (in a great meaſure) to be fulfilled in our Dayes. <hi>There ſhall ariſe falſe Prophets, inſomuch that</hi> (if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) <hi>they ſhall deceive the very Elect,</hi> Math. 24. 24. Is it not time to be Proving, when there is ſuch deceiving? Such accurate deceits, as may not only delude Children and fooles, the Ignorant and unlearned, the carnall and prophane, but, only not, the very Elect. If it ſhould be told that many Cheaters were in a market, and thoſe ſo cunning at it, that they could almoſt cozen the wiſeſt Merchant, would not every one looke well to his bargain, what he bought or how he ſold. Or if it ſhould be ſayd, that much counterfeit and baſe Money is coyned, and that ſo skilfully, that it may paſſe for currant, not only with ſimple Country-men, but almoſt with the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith or the Maſter of the Mint: would not all, be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and trying their money before they receive it in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113433:22"/> Such a ſence is in this warning given by Chriſt, <hi>They ſhall deceive</hi> (if it were poſſible) <hi>the very Elect.</hi> I beleeve deceiving is growne to this height amongſt us; have we not need then every one to be Proving. Wicked Doctrines are damnable, as well as wicked Practiſes; Woe be to thoſe who love Errour, though love may be maintained towards thoſe who Erre. The Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeakes of ſome <hi>who turned the Grace of God into laſciviouſneſse:</hi> If any (which is to be feared, though it cannot be denied them) ſhall turne that grace of favour which God in the Scripture allowes an erring Brother into laſciviouſneſſe; let them tremble at what the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks of the former, <hi>They were of old ordained to this condemnation.</hi> It is bewaileable with teares of blood, that many are in danger to <hi>looſe</hi> all Religion by <hi>ſeeking</hi> it; and that they even let goe what they had, while they are inquiring after what, they have not, and (perhaps) what is not to be had. The Lord diſcover to us all the great and neceſſary duty of <hi>ſeeking,</hi> together with the extreame danger of <hi>wandering:</hi> and teach us to know the <hi>method</hi> of Satan in bringing poore ſouls to ſuch confuſion. That Satan is abroad acting theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices ſhould make us very dilligent in proving what we do, and in doing what we have proved acceptable to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, unleſſe we prove what we doe, we ſhall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> meerly depend upon others for what we do. <hi>Let every man</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>prove his owne worke, and then ſhall he have rejoycing in himſelfe alone and not in others. Gal.</hi> 6. 4. But may a man rejoyce in himſelfe? The Prophet cautions us, <hi>Let not the wiſe man glory in his wiſdome, nor the ſtrong man in his ſtrength, nor the rich</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113433:23"/> 
               <hi>rich man in his riches,</hi> Ier. 9. 23. 'Tis true, we muſt not glory in our ſelves in oppoſition to Chriſt, ſuch glorying is no glory, <hi>He that gloryeth must glory in the Lord:</hi> But we may glory or rejoyce in our ſelves in oppoſition to men; The <hi>other</hi> in the text alleadged, is another man, ſome man of greater learning and wiſdome then our ſelves, ſome man whom we greatly reverence and eſteem, and therefore rejoyce in what we hold or practice, not becauſe we our ſelves ſee the ground of it, but becauſe ſuch a man holds, and practiſes it. Thus the miſled Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts cry out, <hi>Auguſtine, Hierome, Gregorie, Chryſoſtome, &amp;c.</hi> The moſt learned names in the ſeverall ages of the Church, held thus, practiſed this, (though that's denyed them) yet thus they cry, and rejoyce in one another.</p>
            <p>This is to rejoyce in another and not in our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Now then, let every man <hi>Prove his owne worke,</hi> that is, ſtudy, to <hi>be able to give a reaſon as of the hope that is in him, ſo of the worke or practiſe that is held forth by him;</hi> and then we ſhall not rejoyce in others, that is, boaſt that we doe, what ſuch holy and learned men doe, <hi>They are on our ſide;</hi> But we ſhall <hi>rejoyce in our ſelves,</hi> that is, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding with our own eyes the beauty, and finding with our own underſtanding the grounds of thoſe things in the word of God, which wee hold forth in opinion or in practice.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, till we do what is acceptable to the Lord, we <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> cannot expect, the Lord ſhould doe what is acceptable to us. We know he hath done many things very grievous unto us. Is warre acceptable to us? or, are the effects of it: Slaying of men, firing of houſes, ſpoyling of eſtates, acceptable to us? Had we proved what is acceptable to the Lord, wee had not taſted what is ſo unacceptable to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113433:23"/> our ſelves. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> walked contrary to God, then God walked contrary to them, <hi>Lev. 26. 40. 41. If they ſhall confeſſe that they have walked contrary unto me, and that I alſo have walked contrary unto them. With the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God ſhewes himſelfe froward,</hi> Pſal. 18. 26. He can diſpleaſe us, as eaſily as we diſpleaſe him. The ſpeedieſt way then to obtaine what is good in our eyes, is to be doing what is good in his. <hi>O that my people had hearkned unto me, and Iſrael had walked in my wayes,</hi> Pſal. 81. 3. What then? <hi>I ſhould ſoone have ſubdued their Enemies, and turned my hand against their adverſaries. He ſhould have ſed them alſo with the fineſt of the wheat, and with honey out of the ſtony rocke ſhould I have ſatisfied thee, verſ.</hi> 14. 16. When we hearken to God, hee quickly heares us, and when we walke in his wayes, mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſes ours. Our enemies who have begun to fall, ſhall fall more by the command of CHRIST, if we ſhew our ſelves <hi>friends to Christ, by doing whatſoever he hath commanded us,</hi> (Joh. 15. 14.) Many places which fed on Gall and wormwood, have now (bleſſed be God) Bread to eate; but he will feed us all with the fineſt of the Wheat, and the ſweeteſt of the Honey, he will give us not only what is acceptable but delightfull, if we walke before him with refined lives, and draw neere to him in purified ordinances, daily proving, approving, and practiſing, what is acceptable to the Lord.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
